<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Becoming a Programmer Blog</title>
        <link>https://becomingaprogrammer.net/blog</link>
        <description>Becoming a Programmer Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Welcome to The Becoming a Programmer Academy]]></title>
            <link>https://becomingaprogrammer.net/blog/welcome</link>
            <guid>https://becomingaprogrammer.net/blog/welcome</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Welcome to The Becoming a Programmer Academy.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to <strong>The Becoming a Programmer Academy</strong>.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="introduction">Introduction<a href="#introduction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction" title="Direct link to Introduction">​</a></h2><p>I have been playing around with the idea to put to paper what I have learned over the years in terms of software development. The problem is that it is such a vast field and, after 35+ years, I have quite a bit to share. So, how to do? Then it dawned on me. I need to create a complete pre-university level course that will teach you how to build industry-standard enterprise applications, resulting in you becoming a full stack software developer. But, it has to be different from the other course available.  </p><p>There are many courses teaching you how to learn the Java programming language, for example. Using a carpentry analogy, for me, learning Java is like learning how to use a hammer. The problem is that you are not really interested in hammers. Rather, you are interested in making furniture. By the way, if you make hammers for a living, this whole analogy of mine falls flat on its face.</p><p>It turns out that learning to use a hammer is just a necessary skill required in the furniture making process. So, you can be a master hammer swinger (if that is a thing), and at the same time have no clue how to make a table. So, I decided that the focus of the Becoming a Programmer Academy must be to teach you how to make furniture and in the process learn how to use a hammer. Now, obviously, you have to replace the word "hammer" with "Java" and the word "furniture" with software applications.</p><p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> I suck at carpentry! So, I am <strong>not</strong> going to teach you how to build tables and chairs and stuff. For that, you can have a look at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carpentry" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Carpentry</a>. On this website, I am going to teach you how to build software applications. Enterprise applications to be specific.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="pre-university-level">Pre-University Level<a href="#pre-university-level" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Pre-University Level" title="Direct link to Pre-University Level">​</a></h2><p>I said that this must be a pre-university level. What does that even mean? Who knows? It's just something I made up. That said, let me explain what I mean. </p><p>After I have done my two pharmacy degrees in the 80's, I went back to university to study computer science. Also, both my kids studied/study computer science at university. In all three cases I found that a certain amount of knowledge would be highly beneficial BEFORE you go to university. However, most students do not have that knowledge. They simply get thrown into the deep end and either sink or swim. Many sink, unfortunately. </p><p>So the main aim with this website is to give you that knowledge. But it must also be sufficient if you decide never to attend university. The other benefit is that this website may save you a fortune in future expenses. If you don't like the content on this site, you're going to hate what they teach you at university for sure. So, this may be a good place to find out if this programming thing is for you. It certainly is not everybody's cup of tea.    </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="software-developer">Software Developer<a href="#software-developer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Software Developer" title="Direct link to Software Developer">​</a></h2><p>The intention is to transition you over time: </p><ul><li>from zero to coder</li><li>from coder to programmer</li><li>from programmer to developer</li></ul><p>Please note, that for most purposes, these terms, code, programmer and developer, especially the last two, means pretty much the same thing in the real world. I am distinguishing them simply to show progress, nothing else.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="zero-to-coder">Zero to Coder<a href="#zero-to-coder" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Zero to Coder" title="Direct link to Zero to Coder">​</a></h3><p>We will start at the very beginning with a Big Picture overview of where programming fits into the world of Information Technology. Then we will do a number of fundamental courses teaching you the very basics of programming. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="coder-to-programmer">Coder to Programmer<a href="#coder-to-programmer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Coder to Programmer" title="Direct link to Coder to Programmer">​</a></h3><p>Once you know the basics, you will be able to come up with programming ideas of your own and be able to write small albeit real applications.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="programmer-to-developer">Programmer to Developer<a href="#programmer-to-developer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Programmer to Developer" title="Direct link to Programmer to Developer">​</a></h3><p>This is where we want to get to. At this level you know about front-end technologies, back-end technologies, programming languages, libraries, frameworks, databases, version control, testing, etc. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="enterprise-applications">Enterprise Applications<a href="#enterprise-applications" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Enterprise Applications" title="Direct link to Enterprise Applications">​</a></h2><p>I have always written applications of businesses, either in the medical or financial/insurance markets. These types os real-world systems are called enterprise systems or line-of-business applications as they typically support the day-to-day operations of businesses. Please note that I sometimes use the term <em>application</em> and other times <em>system</em>. These terms are used synonymously. Also, most younger programmers will use the term <em>app</em> in place of <em>application</em>. </p><p>You will find that sometimes more than one term is used to mean the same thing, while other times a single term will be used to mean different things. The term API is one of those terms which can mean any number of things. However, we will tackle that in one of the courses. </p><p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> I have never written any games, so, I am not the person to teach you how to build games and similar types of apps. The majority of this site may be a waste of your time if you want to go into that direction. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="information-systems">Information Systems<a href="#information-systems" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Information Systems" title="Direct link to Information Systems">​</a></h3><p>The type of enterprise systems that I build (or program or develop) all fall under the category of Information Systems. You find these systems everywhere. Every time your buy from the local grocer, or you do a bank transaction at the ATM, or you buy something online, or you pay somebody via something like PayPal, you are interacting with an Information System of some sort.</p><p>These systems usually have at least three components, the user interface, the business logic, and the database.</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="user-interface">User Interface<a href="#user-interface" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to User Interface" title="Direct link to User Interface">​</a></h4><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="industry-standard">Industry Standard<a href="#industry-standard" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Industry Standard" title="Direct link to Industry Standard">​</a></h3><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="full-stack">Full Stack<a href="#full-stack" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Full Stack" title="Direct link to Full Stack">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="front-end-developer">Front End Developer<a href="#front-end-developer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Front End Developer" title="Direct link to Front End Developer">​</a></h3><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="back-end-developer">Back End Developer<a href="#back-end-developer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Back End Developer" title="Direct link to Back End Developer">​</a></h3><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="full-stack-developer">Full Stack Developer<a href="#full-stack-developer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Full Stack Developer" title="Direct link to Full Stack Developer">​</a></h3><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>general</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>